Finding Aid for the Kenneth N. Trueblood Papers LSC.0589
UCLA Library Special Collections
Kenneth N. Trueblood papers
1947-1998
UCLA Library Special Collections
Trueblood, Kenneth, N.
LSC.0589
34.8 Linear Feet (31 record storage cartons, 6 document boxes, 1 flat box, and 1 oversize flat box)
Kenneth N. Trueblood, a pioneering crystallographer, contributed to research that led to two Nobel Prizes, received awards for his renowned teaching, and served as Chair of the Department of Chemistry at UCLA and Dean of the College of Letters and Science at UCLA. The collection contains his research files, laboratory notebooks, computer programs, lecture notes, speeches, correspondence, grant applications, annotated publications, and documents related to his involvement with professional crystallography organizations.
Conditions on Access
Open for research. All requests to access special collections materials must be made in advance using the request button located on this page.
Provenance/Source of Acquisition
Jean Trueblood and Emily Maverick, 1999.
UCLA Catalog Record ID
UCLA Catalog Record ID: 9947696423606533
Biography/History
Kenneth N. Trueblood, a pioneering crystallographer known also for his exceptional teaching, was born on April 24, 1920 in Dobbs Ferry, New York. He received his A.B. from Harvard College in 1941 and his Ph.D. from California Institute of Technology for research in chromatography and spectrophotometry in 1947. However, inspired by the ground-breaking work of his professor Linus Pauling, Trueblood went on to work in crystallography. After two years of post-doctoral work at Caltech, he became an instructor in the Department of Chemistry at UCLA in 1949 and was made an assistant professor in 1950. He became a full professor in 1960 and was awarded the newly created UCLA Distinguished Teaching Award in 1961. This same year, he also became President of the American Crystallographic Association, which he co-founded. He served as Chair of the Department of Chemistry at UCLA from 1965-1970 and became Dean of the UCLA College of Letters and Science in 1971. Teaching throughout his time as Chair and Dean, he stepped down from his position as Dean in 1974 in order to return to teaching full-time. However, he returned to administrative service as Chair of the Academic Senate from 1983-1984 and chaired the Department of Chemistry once again from 1990-1991.
Trueblood's research contributed to the Nobel prize-winning research of Dorothy Hodgkin and Donald J. Cram. After receiving a Fulbright research award, Trueblood worked with Hodgkin from 1956-1957 at Oxford on the chemical structure of vitamin B-12. Hodgkin was awarded a Nobel Prize in Chemistry in 1964 for discovering the structure of vitamin B-12. Trueblood recommended Cram for consideration for the Nobel Prize, which he received in 1987.
A popular and respected teacher, Trueblood was known for his warmth, dedication, personability and for learning all of his students' names in classes that often contained over 350 students. Trueblood continued his research through the end of his life, and his last paper, with Verner Schomaker, was published posthumously in Acta Cryst. Kenneth N. Trueblood died in Los Angeles on May 7, 1998.
Scope and Content
The Kenneth N. Trueblood papers include materials that document his research, including computer programs, notes and programs related to the discovery of the structure of vitamin B-12, lab notebooks, and grant applications; correspondence; UCLA Department of Chemistry files; lecture notes, including those from his studies under Linus Pauling; speeches Trueblood gave in academic and professional settings; annotated publications; professional organization materials related to Acta Crystallographica, where he served in an editorial capacity, and the American Crystallographic Association, which he co-founded; and photos, awards, and memorials.
Organization and Arrangement
The collection has been arranged in the following series:
1. Computer program print-outs.
2. Correspondence.
3. Publications.
4. Talks.
5. Professional organization files.
6. UCLA Department of Chemistry files.
7. Grant applications.
8. Lecture notes and teaching materials.
9. Photos, awards and memorials.
Trueblood, Kenneth, N. -- Archives.; Crystallographers -- California -- Los Angeles -- Archives.; University of California, Los Angeles -- Department of Chemistry and Biochemistry -- Faculty -- Archives.
- Computer program print-outs., 1953-1998
  Scope and Content
  Print-outs of computer programs developed and used by Trueblood to determine three-dimensional electron-density maps from crystallographic data. Materials also include related notes, correspondence, flow-charts, instruction manuals and articles. Boxes 2-14 include work with colleagues Emily F. Maverick and Carolyn B. Knobler.
  - B-12., 1953-1956. (Box 1)
    Materials include the computer program and its results for the crystal structure of Vitamin B-12, for which Dorothy Hodgkin of Oxford University won the Nobel Prize in 1964. Materials also include a paper by Robert A. Sparks and Richard J. Prosen on the subject: Some Sleek, Successful, Super-sonic, Solid Structure, SWAC Summations, Seldom Seen so Simply Shown, for Functional Fouriers plus Precise Pattersons and Flow Diagrams for the First Pass of Three Dimensional Fourier Routine.
  - TCNE-MPCP, CN84L, HEX100., 1970-1975, 1988-1990. (Box 2)
    Materials include four TCNE-MPCP annotated data collection notebooks.
  - FMLS650, XRAYBU, XRAY11, SHELX76, HACNA., 1971, 1975-1976, 1978-1987, 1989. (Box 3)
    In addition to print-outs, materials include correspondence between Trueblood and Maverick concerning the FMLS650 program, a Memorex magnetic tape for XRAYBU and XRAY11, correspondence between Trueblood and Professor G.M. Sheldrick concerning the SHELX76 program tests and a HACNA data collection file.
  - SB596-563, D20P, N2OTBP, CRK21., 1977, 1982-1998. (Box 4)
    Materials also include folders on the following CRYP structures: CRYPB, CRYPCS, CRYP2, CRYPNA and CRYP1.
  - ABRANS, CARN, MCARS, PAUL2, SB596, DB4FN., 1978, 1983, 1992-1998. (Box 5)
  - MPCP, A3U2E, D2OP, HA3U, ARTZA4., 1979-1985. (Box 6)
    In addition to print-outs, correspondence and notes, materials also include one box of X-Ray Film images labeled 2.2.-m.p.-cyclophane. I.II 66.
  - HC0, HAC2, HACF6., 1979-1985. (Box 7)
    The majority of these print-outs include annotations by Emily Maverick.
  - DGRUS, DGRUSP, DG2H., 1980, 1989, 1993. (Box 8)
    In addition to print-outs, materials also include correspondence between Trueblood and Maverick and colorized drawings of molecular structures.
  - DISHBR., 1981, 1983, 1985, 1987. (Box 9)
    Materials also include Trueblood's handwritten SCUP tables annotated by Maverick.
  - RBM, RBM2, RBM3, RBM4., 1984-1997. (Box 10)
    In addition to print-outs, materials also include correspondence between Trueblood and Verner Schomaker, a copy of the National Institute of Standards and Technology (NIST) Technical Note 1290 NIST LATTICE: A Program to Analyze Lattice Relationships, a copy of MITHRIL: A Computer Program for the Automatic Solution of Crystal Structures from X-Ray Data and notes, calculations and correspondence concerning Ferrocene.
  - THMA11, RBM4., 1984-1997. (Box 11)
    Materials include correspondence between Trueblood and Verner Schomaker concerning thermal motion programs.
  - THM1, THM14C, THMA110, THMA12., 1987-1988, 1992-1997. (Box 12)
  - K1-K2., 1987-1988, 1994, 1998. (Box 13)
    Many print-outs are annotated by Trueblood and include handwritten calculations.
  - RHPEV, YOON2RN, CE2, CE6, BTE, BILI., 1989, 1991, 1996-1997. (Box 14)
    Print-outs include dividers and annotations by Emily Maverick.
  - Copy II X-SWAC write-up. (Box 20, Folder 24)
  - Copy I X-SWAC routine. (Box 20, Folder 25)
  - X-SWAC commands/ Copy I. (Box 20, Folder 26)
  - Anisotropic Temp Factors. (Box 20, Folder 27)
  - [Least squares]...applications. (Box 20, Folder 28)
  - XTALLOG computing. (Box 20, Folder 29)
  - Crystal structure refinement - equations for Cruickshank. (Box 20, Folder 30)
  - Least squares. (Box 20, Folder 31)
  - M.O. calculations. (Box 21, Folder 1)
  - PCOR and libration-corrected intramolecular geometry. (Box 21, Folder 2)
  - Molecular motion in crystals TLS correspondence. (Box 21, Folder 3)
  - THMB/THMI (BM) correspondence. (Box 21, Folder 4)
  - THMB: Parameter sets. (Box 21, Folder 5)
  - Aniso. thermal parameters. (Box 21, Folder 6)
  - THMVIO distributions., 1996 (Box 21, Folder 7-10)
  - THMB parameters. II., 1977-1978 (Box 21, Folder 11)
  - THMI/THMB program requests and responses thereto. (Box 21, Folder 12-13)
  - Reduced Cells ("REDUCET")., 1978-1991 (Box 21, Folder 14)
  - SLPFP., 1983-1984 (Box 21, Folder 16)
  - PARST. (Box 21, Folder 25)
  - For 2080 files: program requests., 1965-1973 (Box 21, Folder 29-30)
  - Larry Scott (K2)., 1988; 1994 (Box 27, Folder 5)
  - Burnham - absorption., Ca. 1965 (Box 25, Folder 7)
  - CFOURE., 1963 (Box 25, Folder 11)
  - Chastain-Boonstra-Stewart Phase. (Box 25, Folder 12)
  - CSFPUB. (Box 25, Folder 13)
  - DIRDIF/TRADIR., 1981 (Box 25, Folder 14)
  - FMLS., Spring 1976 (Box 25, Folder 17)
  - Lipscomb superposition. (Box 25, Folder 25)
  - [Computer] coding general routines., Ca. 1955-1959 (Box 25, Folder 28)
  - VAX programs. (Box 26, Folder 3)
  - (VAX) Fortran., 1982 (Box 26, Folder 4)
  - Geotab shelxl orfls hpos args hacf_. (Box 26, Folder 5)
  - Shelxs-86. (Box 26, Folder 6)
  - Shelx-76. (Box 26, Folder 7)
  - Ortep; ortepk., 1965 (Box 26, Folder 8-9)
  - Ortep-II., 1976 Mar. (Box 26, Folder 10)
  - VAX procedures. (Box 26, Folder 11-12)
  - Excel. (Box 26, Folder 13)
  - EDT. (Box 26, Folder 14)
  - Erice tutorial. (Box 26, Folder 15)
- Correspondence.
  Correspondence from Trueblood acting in his capacity as a researcher, administrator, and instructor. Materials also include accompanying notes and articles as well as personal correspondence.
  - General.
    - Acta-Cryst. (Box 15, Folder 1)
    - Misc. A. (Box 15, Folder 2)
    - Battelle, Linda Forrest. (Box 15, Folder 3)
    - Beckman, Arnold/ Beckman Instruments, Inc. (Box 15, Folder 4)
    - Bekoe, D. Adzei. (Box 15, Folder 5)
    - Bernstein, Joel. (Box 15, Folder 6-7)
    - Bonner, William A. (Box 15, Folder 8)
    - Breyer, (Wild Spickler), Patricia. (Box 15, Folder 9)
    - Brock, Carolyn P. (Box 15, Folder 10)
    - Burgi, Hans-Beat. (Box 15, Folder 11)
    - Byrn, Stephen R. (Box 15, Folder 12)
    - Misc. B. (Box 15, Folder 13)
    - Cruickshank, Durward W. J. (Box 15, Folder 14)
    - Misc. C. (Box 15, Folder 15)
    - Davis, Donner (Strong). (Box 15, Folder 16)
    - Donnay, Gabrielle. (Box 15, Folder 17)
    - Misc. D. (Box 15, Folder 18)
    - Easter, David. (Box 15, Folder 19)
    - Misc. E. (Box 15, Folder 20)
    - Misc. F. (Box 15, Folder 21)
    - Gantzel, Peter. (Box 15, Folder 22)
    - Glusker, Jenny Pickworth. (Box 15, Folder 23)
    - Goldberg, Israel. (Box 15, Folder 24-25)
    - Goldsmith, Elizabeth. (Box 16, Folder 1)
    - Grob, Cyril A. (Box 16, Folder 2)
    - Misc. G. (Box 16, Folder 3)
    - Helgeson, Roger. (Box 16, Folder 4)
    - Hirshfeld, Fred L. (Box 16, Folder 5)
    - Hodgkin, Dorothy. (Box 16, Folder 6-8)
    - Hoffmann, Roald. (Box 16, Folder 9)
    - Hakon, Hope. (Box 16, Folder 10)
    - Misc. H. (Box 16, Folder 11)
    - Misc. I. (Box 16, Folder 12)
    - Johnson, Carroll K. (Box 16, Folder 13)
    - Julian, Maureen. (Box 16, Folder 14)
    - Misc. J. (Box 16, Folder 15)
    - Kennard, Olga. (Box 16, Folder 16)
    - Kuchitsu, Kozo. (Box 16, Folder 17)
    - Misc. K. (Box 16, Folder 18)
    - Laing, Mary and Michael. (Box 16, Folder 19)
    - Laing, Mary Burke. (Box 16, Folder 20)
    - Laing, Michael. (Box 16, Folder 21)
    - Lightner, David. (Box 16, Folder 22)
    - Lipscomb, William N. (Box 16, Folder 23)
    - Long, Robert E. (Box 16, Folder 24)
    - Lurie, Gwyn. (Box 16, Folder 25)
    - Misc. L. (Box 16, Folder 26)
    - Marsh, Richard E. (Box 16, Folder 27)
    - Mayer, Stanley W. (Box 16, Folder 28)
    - Meyers, Michelle. (Box 16, Folder 29)
    - Misc. M. (Box 16, Folder 30)
    - National Science Foundation. (Box 16, Folder 31)
    - Misc. N. (Box 16, Folder 32)
    - Misc. O. (Box 16, Folder 33)
    - Palenik, Gus. (Box 16, Folder 34)
    - Pauling, Linus. (Box 16, Folder 35)
    - Pauling National Medal of Science. (Box 16, Folder 36)
    - Pauley, G.S. (Box 16, Folder 37)
    - Perrin, Marilyn. (Box 16, Folder 38)
    - Pecsok, Robert L. (Box 17, Folder 1)
    - Pedersen, Berit F. (Box 17, Folder 2)
    - Polycrystal Book Service. (Box 17, Folder 3)
    - Postdoctoral applications x-ray crystallography 1977-. (Box 17, Folder 4)
    - Prosen, Rosemary and Richard. (Box 17, Folder 5)
    - Misc. P. (Box 17, Folder 6)
    - Misc. Q. (Box 17, Folder 7)
    - Referee reports (1982-1985). (Box 17, Folder 8)
    - Robin, M. B. (Box 17, Folder 9)
    - Misc. R. (Box 17, Folder 10)
    - Sawyer, Donald T. (Box 17, Folder 11)
    - Saxon, David. (Box 17, Folder 12)
    - Sayre, David. (Box 17, Folder 13)
    - Schomaker, Verner. (Box 17, Folder 14)
    - Schwarzenbach, Dieter. (Box 17, Folder 15)
    - Seff, Karl. (Box 17, Folder 16)
    - Seiler, Paul. (Box 17, Folder 17)
    - Seltzer, Joanne. (Box 17, Folder 18)
    - Seltzer, Sharon. (Box 17, Folder 19)
    - Sheffer, Eli. (Box 17, Folder 20)
    - Shmueli, Uri. (Box 17, Folder 21)
    - Shoemaker, David P. (Box 17, Folder 22)
    - Smithson, Luther H. (Box 17, Folder 23)
    - Sparks, Robert A. (Box 17, Folder 24)
    - Sporer, Alfred Herbert. (Box 17, Folder 25)
    - Stapleton, George. (Box 17, Folder 26)
    - Stezowski, John. (Box 17, Folder 27)
    - Stone, Diane Spierer. (Box 17, Folder 28)
    - Sturgeon, Kathy Sue. (Box 17, Folder 29)
    - Misc. S. (Box 17, Folder 30)
    - Misc. T. (Box 17, Folder 31)
    - Misc. U. (Box 17, Folder 32)
    - Misc. V. (Box 17, Folder 33)
    - Waser, Jurg. (Box 17, Folder 34)
    - Wilson, M. Kent. (Box 17, Folder 35)
    - Wingrove, Alan S. (Box 17, Folder 36)
    - Misc. W. (Box 17, Folder 37)
    - Misc. X, Y, Z. (Box 17, Folder 38)
  - UCLA.
    - UCLA College of Letters and Sciences. (Box 18, Folder 21)
    - Letters and Sciences related. (Box 18, Folder 22)
    - Dept. of Intercollegiate Athletics [Coach Wooden correspondence]., 1952 Jan. 4 (Box 18, Folder 23)
    - Correspondence regarding J. Kirshenbaum and J. Szenjntop. (Box 18, Folder 24)
    - Gillespie, Richard B. (Box 18, Folder 25)
    - Hanke, Gunther. (Box 18, Folder 26)
    - Murphy, Franklin D. (Box 18, Folder 27)
    - Parker, Keith. (Box 18, Folder 28)
    - Saxon, David. (Box 18, Folder 29)
    - Seymour, Dorothy. (Box 18, Folder 30)
    - [Charles E. Young]. (Box 18, Folder 31)
    - Zentner, Jules. (Box 18, Folder 32)
    - Dean of Students Office. (Box 18, Folder 33)
    - Student Welfare Committee., 1958-1960 (Box 18, Folder 34)
    - 9th All University Faculty Davis Conference, 1953-1954 (Box 18, Folder 35)
    - Univ. confi. (Box 36, Folder 1)
    - [Chuck Young re: Angela Davis]. (Box 36, Folder 2)
    - UCLA people and parties. (Box 36, Folder 3-4)
    - UCLA corresp. (Box 36, Folder 5-8)
    - Letters rec'd re: resignation as Dean. (Box 36, Folder 9)
    - UCLA employment. (Box 36, Folder 10)
    - SWAC. (Box 36, Folder 11)
    - Organization of x-ray facility. (Box 36, Folder 12)
    - Emails. (Box 36, Folder 13)
    - [Cram and KNT re: peer review pub.]. (Box 36, Folder 14)
    - Messages. (Box 36, Folder 15)
    - UCLA chemists - news story. (Box 36, Folder 16)
    - Corresp. March 1989. (Box 36, Folder 17)
    - Wiseman, Charles. (Box 36, Folder 18)
    - "Chem One." (Box 36, Folder 19)
    - Cambridge file deposition. (Box 25, Folder 8)
  - UCLA Chemistry Department.
    - Dan Atkinson. (Box 18, Folder 3)
    - Carter, Emily A. (Box 18, Folder 4)
    - Cram, Donald J. (Box 18, Folder 5)
    - Nomination of Donald J. Cram for Nobel Prize for Chemistry., 1978, 1984 (Box 18, Folder 6)
    - Eisenberg, David. (Box 18, Folder 7)
    - Knobler, Carolyn B. (Box 18, Folder 8)
    - Liu, You-Xi. (Box 18, Folder 9)
    - Maverick, Emily. (Box 25, Folder 24, Box 18, Folder 10-11)
    - McCullough, J. D. (Box 18, Folder 12)
    - Mirskaya, Kira. (Box 18, Folder 13)
    - Mirsky, Kira and Michael. (Box 18, Folder 14)
    - Murphy, Mike. (Box 18, Folder 15)
    - Ramsey, J. B. (Box 18, Folder 16)
    - Rees, D. C. (Box 18, Folder 17)
    - Russell, Arlene. (Box 18, Folder 18)
    - Scott, Robert L. (Box 18, Folder 19)
    - Weiss, Robert. (Box 18, Folder 20)
    - Research Group., 1982-1984 (Box 26, Folder 18)
    - Crystallography Group. (Box 26, Folder 19)
    - Cram Group., 1982-1983 (Box 26, Folder 19)
  - Personal.
    - Letters and cards. (Box 36, Folder 20-22)
    - Verner Schomaker obituary. (Box 36, Folder 23)
    - KNT - March C and C responses. (Box 36, Folder 24)
    - KNT stationery. (Box 26, Folder 16)
  - Professional.
    - Hodgkin, Dorothy Crowfoot. (Box 36, Folder 25-26)
    - Caltech. (Box 36, Folder 27)
    - Belov, N.V. (Box 36, Folder 28)
    - Hanson, A. W., 1970 (Box 25, Folder 15)
- Publications.
  Reprints of Trueblood's publications, editions of textbooks he authored, and copies of articles he collected categorized by subject or author.
  - Chromatographic Properties of Silicic Acid-Celite., 1949 Sep. (Box 19, Folder 1)
    Master reprint number 1.
  - Master reprint [#2-10]. (Box 19, Folder 2)
  - Master reprint [#11-20]. (Box 19, Folder 3)
  - Master reprint [#21-30]. (Box 19, Folder 4)
  - Master reprint [#31-40]. (Box 19, Folder 5)
  - Master reprint [#41-50]. (Box 19, Folder 6)
  - Master reprint [#51-60]. (Box 19, Folder 7)
  - Master reprint [#61-70]. (Box 19, Folder 8)
  - Master reprint [#71-80]. (Box 19, Folder 9)
  - Master reprint [#81-90]. (Box 19, Folder 10)
  - Master reprint [#91-100]. (Box 19, Folder 11)
  - Master reprint [#101-110]. (Box 19, Folder 12)
  - Master reprint [#111-120]. (Box 19, Folder 13)
  - Master reprint [#121-130]. (Box 19, Folder 14)
  - Master reprint [#131-]. (Box 19, Folder 15)
  - KNT reprints. (Box 19, Folder 16-17)
  - Binaphthy Crowns MS., 1981 (Box 21, Folder 31)
  - Hemispherand MSS. (Box 21, Folder 32)
  - A3U2BA., 1986 (Box 21, Folder 33)
  - Spherand MSS. (Box 21, Folder 34)
  - Spherand literature file. (Box 21, Folder 34-35)
  - Hargittai-Kitaigorodsky., 1992 Apr. (Box 22, Folder 17)
  - Trueblood publications in Acta Cryst. (Box 27, Folder 8-10)
  - Crowns, others. (Box 23, Folder 1)
  - Crown Ethers and Related V./ DJC Group (II). (Box 23, Folder 2-3)
  - Crown Ethers and Related III./ Cram group. (Box 23, Folder 4-5)
  - Crown Ethers and Related IV. IG, KNT... (Box 23, Folder 6-8)
  - Cavitauds/ DJC group (III). (Box 23, Folder 9)
  - Lehn [Jean-Marie] et al/ Crowns Cryptands. (Box 23, Folder 10)
  - Cruikshank [D. W. J.]. (Box 23, Folder 11)
  - Direct Methods: Woolfson et al. (Box 23, Folder 13)
  - Pitt - Direct Methods. (Box 23, Folder 14)
  - J. Dunitz I. (Box 23, Folder 15-16)
  - J. Dunitz II. (Box 23, Folder 17)
  - J. Dunitz III. (Box 23, Folder 18-19)
  - J. Dunitz IV. (Box 23, Folder 20-21)
  - Eisenberg. (Box 23, Folder 22)
  - Error's, ESD's, Hamilton Tests, Normal Prob Plots. (Box 24, Folder 1)
  - J. Glusker. (Box 24, Folder 4)
  - I. Goldberg. (Box 24, Folder 5)
  - H-bonds: Ljubljana Conference., 1957 (Box 24, Folder 6)
  - F. Hirshfeld. (Box 24, Folder 7)
  - Lattice Dynamics. (Box 24, Folder 8-9)
  - Leiserowitz. (Box 24, Folder 10-11)
  - Dunitz and Dornberger-Schiff. (Box 24, Folder 12)
  - Linus Pauling. (Box 24, Folder 13)
  - Radii can der Waals Ionic. (Box 24, Folder 14)
  - C. Scheringer. (Box 24, Folder 15)
  - U. Shmueli, I. Goldberg (non-crown). (Box 24, Folder 16)
  - Charles E. Strouse. (Box 24, Folder 17)
  - Jurg Waser. (Box 24, Folder 18)
  - Ibers scattering factors. (Box 25, Folder 20)
  - Patterson reprints: many AA-Peptide papers here., Ca. 1950s (Box 25, Folder 26)
    Scope and Contents
    Includes holograph notes by Trueblood.
  - Patterson search programs literature. (Box 25, Folder 27)
  - Relevant literature., Ca. 1979-1986 (Box 27, Folder 14)
  - [Journal reprints of collaboration with Hodgkin]. (Box 37, Folder 1)
    Reprints include the following articles: "The structure of vitamin B-12: IV. The X-ray analysis of air-dried crystals of B-12," "The structure of vitamin B-12: V. The structure of the air-dried crystals of vitamin B-12" and "The Crystal Structure of a Calciferol Derivative."
  - KNT annotated reprints. (Box 37, Folder 2, 21-22)
  - [Torsional Motion...]. (Box 37, Folder 3)
  - [Publications and notes]. (Box 37, Folder 4)
    Materials include Trueblood's notes and copies of "physics today" periodicals.
  - [An aromatic hydrocarbon...]. (Box 37, Folder 5)
  - Reprints and gray lit. (Box 37, Folder 6-12)
    Materials include reprints from the following: Linus Pauling, Donald J. Cram, Willard F. Libby, Rosalind E. Franklin, Francis Crick and James Watson.
  - McTague - Dynamics of Liquids and Solids. (Box 37, Folder 13)
  - The Texbook. (Box 37, Folder 14)
  - [On the correlation of internal torsional...]. (Box 37, Folder 15)
  - [A rerefinement of the crystal structure...]. (Box 37, Folder 16)
  - Articles collected by KNT. (Box 37, Folder 17)
  - ACA newsletter. (Box 37, Folder 18)
    Newsletter included feature article on the selection of Jenny Glusker and Trueblood to receive ACA's Fankuchen Award for their contributions to crystallography.
  - Digital Computers in Crystallography. (Box 37, Folder 19)
  - [Abstracts and reports]. (Box 37, Folder 20)
  - Notes on Glusker and Trueblood 3rd edition. (Box 37, Folder 23-24)
  - Stanley W. Mayer thesis. (Box 37, Folder 25)
    Trueblood and Donald J. Cram were committee members for Mayer's thesis concerning the application of SWAC to crystal structure calculations and the crystal structures of sulfamide and cyclopropylamine hydrochloride.
  - Chapters for Chemistry 1A. (Box 37, Folder 26)
    Jurg Waser and Trueblood's first portion of a projected textbook for a first-year college or university chemistry course.
  - Chem One. (Box 37, Folder 27-29)
    Materials include Trueblood's book with Jurg Waser and Charles M. Knobler as well as the instructor's manual and solutions and supplementary material.
  - Crystal Structure Analysis: A Primer. (Box 37, Folder 30-31)
    The first and second edition of Trueblood's book with Jenny Pickworth Glusker.
  - Polarized Light Microscopy. (Box 37, Folder 32)
  - Self-organization of Matter and Early Evolution of Life. (Box 37, Folder 33)
    This preprint is inscribed "Cordially, Hans" by author Hans Kuhn.
  - Modern Topics in Biochemistry. (Box 37, Folder 34)
    This first edition was a gift from P.D. Boyer on September 1, 1968.
- Talks.
  Typed speeches, handwritten talks, related notes and a recording of one of his UCLA presentations.
  - General talks to students. (Box 20, Folder 9)
  - Molec Motion in Crystals: Zurich seminars. (Box 21, Folder 26)
  - CIT, UCLA: f, Barriers from x-ray data., 1982-1983 (Box 21, Folder 27)
  - Talk on Thermal Motion (Stuttgart). (Box 21, Folder 28)
  - American Chemical Society student affiliates. (Box 35, Folder 1)
  - Calif. Assoc. of Chemistry Teachers talk. (Box 35, Folder 2)
  - Cram research group, talks to... (Box 35, Folder 3)
  - Education at UCLA. (Box 35, Folder 4)
  - Erice, Italy conferences. (Box 35, Folder 5)
  - Liquid crystals talk. (Box 35, Folder 6)
  - Orientation for new students. (Box 35, Folder 7)
  - South Gate High School talk. (Box 35, Folder 8)
  - Talks: Teaching, careers, orientation. (Box 35, Folder 9-10)
  - Teaching assistants orientation talk. (Box 35, Folder 11)
  - UCLA commencement. (Box 35, Folder 12)
  - Talks - clippings, notes. (Box 35, Folder 13-14)
  - KNT notes on symposium talks. (Box 35, Folder 15)
  - K's talk. (Box 35, Folder 16)
  - Trueblood THMA. (Box 35, Folder 17)